Guide to the George P. Garrett Papers, 1929-2008 (bulk 1960-2000)
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
George P. Garrett papers 1929-2008 (bulk 1960-2000)
Garrett, George P., 1929-2008
268 linear feet Extent: 177,929 Items
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
George P. Garrett (1929-2008) was a poet, editor, author, and professor of English. The papers of George P. Garrett span the years 1929 to 2000 with the bulk of the material being dated between 1960 and 1990. The papers were initially collected and assembled by author, bibliographer, and publisher Stuart T. Wright. Wright published a number of Garrett's works at his Palaemon Press and also assembled the Stuart Wright Bibliographic Collection of George Garrett (see related materials held by the Rubenstein Library). Additional materials were received by the Library directly from George Garrett. The papers document Garrett's literary career as an author of novels, short stories, poetry, and dramatic works (including filmscripts) and the tremendous influence he had as an English professor and an editor on an entire generation of writers, particularly in the South. Correspondence with numerous authors, publishers, and educators offers much information about the history of 20th-century Southern literature, publishing, and literary education. The collection is divided into the Writings Series (with subseries of Writings by Garrett, Writings Edited by Garrett, Writings by Others, and Proofs); the Correspondence Series (with 5 subseries of alphabetically and chronologically arranged correspondence); the Audiovisual Material Series; and the Miscellaneous Papers Series.
RL.00438
Language: English.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Also, some materials in this collection are not immediately accessible, because they require further processing before use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The papers of George P. Garrett were collected and assembled by Stuart T. Wright and were acquired as part of the Leona Bowman Carpenter Collection of English and American Literature by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library of Duke University in 1993. Subsequent additions were received as gifts from George Garrett and others between 1993 and 2008.
Biographical Note
1929, June 11 Born in Florida to George Palmer Garrett and Rosalie Toomer Garrett
1946 Graduated from Sewanee Military Academy
1948-1949 Studied at Columbia University
1952 Received BA from Princeton University
1952 Married Susan Parrish Jackson
1953-1955 Served in United States Army, including tour of duty with Occupation Forces in Trieste
1956 Received MA from Princeton University
1956-1960 Assistant Professor, Wesleyan University
1958-1971 U.S. Poetry Editor, Transatlantic Review, Rome, London, New York City
1961-1962 Visiting Lecturer, Rice University
1962-1967 Associate Professor, University of Virginia
1963-1968 Contemporary Poetry Series Editor, University of North Carolina Press
1964-1965 Writer-in-Residence, Princeton University
1967-1971 Professor of English and Director of Writing Program, Hollins College
1970- Contributor Editor, Contempora, Atlanta, Ga.
1971- Contributor Editor, The Film Journal, New York City, N.Y.
1971-1973 Professor of English and Writer-in-Residence, University of South Carolina
1972- Co-editor, Worksheet, Columbia, S.C.
1974-1976 Senior Fellow, Council of the Humanities, Princeton University
1976-1977 Adjunct Professor, School of the Arts, Columbia University
1978-1979 Writer-in-Residence, University of Michigan
1979-1980 Professor of English, Bennington College
1981 Eminent Scholar, Virginia Military Institute
1982-1984 Professor of English, University of Michigan
1984- Henry Hoyns Professor of Creative Writing, University of Virginia
1985 Received Ph.D. from Princeton University
2002-2006 Poet Laureate of Virginia
May 25, 2008 Died
Collection Overview
The papers of George P. Garrett span the years 1929 to 2000 with the bulk of the material being dated between 1960 and 1990. The papers were initially collected and assembled by author, bibliographer, and publisher Stuart T. Wright. Wright published a number of Garrett's works at his Palaemon Press and also assembled the Stuart Wright Bibliographic Collection of George Garrett (see related materials held by the Rubenstein Library). Additional materials were received by the Library directly from George Garrett.
The collection primarily documents Garrett's literary career as an author of novels, short stories, poetry, and dramatic works (including filmscripts) and the tremendous influence he had as an English professor and an editor on an entire generation of writers, particularly in the South. Correspondence with numerous authors, publishers, and educators offers much information about the history of 20th-century Southern literature, publishing, and literary education. The collection is divided into the Writings Series (with subseries of Writings by Garrett, Writings Edited by Garrett, Writings by Others, and Proofs); the Correspondence Series (with 5 subseries of alphabetically and chronologically arranged correspondence); the Audiovisual Material Series; and the Miscellaneous Papers Series.
The Alphabetical Correspondence Subseries: Group A contains letters from numerous contemporary American authors, among them Madison Smartt Bell, who wrote regarding the progress of his fiction, his experience with publishers and literary agents, and his interview with Garrett for Paris Review; and Fred Chappell, whose letters provide commentary on his own works The Inkling and Dagon as well as praise for Garrett's Death of the Fox, The Magic Striptease, and Welcome to the Medicine Show. The Writings by Others Subseries contains Bell's interview with Garrett, in which Garrett discusses his writing process, and critical essays by Fred Chappell (including one on Garrett's The Stranger in the Mirror and one on the work of Sylvia Wilkinson). The Proofs Subseries contains a proof of Reynolds Price's Collected Stories, with brief comments by Garrett.
Garrett's own literary career is documented throughout the collection. The Writings by Garrett Subseries contains manuscripts, typescripts, notes, and drafts of his work, some of it bearing notes for revision. The Chronological Correspondence Subseries contains letters in which Garrett wrote about his works in progress and letters from friends and publishers regarding his work. The comments of noted literary figures regarding Garrett's work frequently appear in letters in the Alphabetical Correspondence Subseries: Group A. This series also affords researchers a detailed view of literary criticism and support exchanged between Garrett and the many authors represented in the collection. His negotiations with publishers are best documented in the Alphabetical Correspondence Subseries: Group B. The Audiovisual Material Series contains some recordings of Garrett reading from his own work.
The Audiovisual Material Series, which contains many recordings of Garrett's lectures, classes, and addresses to groups of writers, students, and literary scholars, documents Garrett's teaching style and his ideas on the teaching of writing. Recordings of lectures and readings by many other well-known authors also appear in this series. Garrett's impact on his students and fellow authors is again visible in the Writings by Others Subseries, which consists of numerous manuscripts, typescripts, and drafts (some bearing notes by Garrett) of work sent to Garrett for commentary and revision.
The addition (Acc. 1998-0356) (5500 items, 15 linear feet; dated 1980-1998 [bulk 1995-1997]) further documents the life, career, and writing of the author and educator. It consists of audiotapes of various authors, including Garrett reading their works; a videocassette entitled The Great Gatsby; printed materials and writings, including published books, journals, drafts, and bound proofs; a large amount of personal and business correspondence; and manuscripts submitted to Garrett for comment.
The addition (Acc. 1999-0268) (1 item, 0.3 linear feet; dated [ca. 1996]) consists of a photocopied typescript of Garrett's novel The King of Babylon Shall Not Come Against You with handwritten annotations.
The addition (Acc. 1999-0379) (450 items, 0.6 linear feet; dated 1956-1972) is primarily comprised of incoming correspondence, chiefly professional; a number of writings are interfiled with or attached to letters. Also included are miscellaneous printed materials such as brochures and clippings.
The addition (Acc. 2000-0085) (9100 items, dated 1964-1999) further documents Garrett's literary career with additional manuscripts, often parts of or related to The King of Babylon Shall not Come Against You. There are audiotapes of readings by Garrett and others, literary correspondence, and clippings.
The addition (Acc. 2000-0303) (15 items, 1 linear foot; dated 1995-2000) documents some of Garrett's writing process and his direct comments in readings and on videotape. Included are page proofs and a revised typescript of The King of Babylon Shall Not Come Against You, a revised typescript of Entered From the Sun, 11 cassette tapes of readings and lectures presumably by Garrett, and a videotape entitled Writers - East of the Blue Ridge on which he is interviewed.
The addition (Acc. 2002-0034) (1 item, 1 lin. ft.; dated 2002) comprises an uncorrected page proof, with color cover, for Garrett's Going to See the Elephant: Pieces of a Writing Life. This accession is unprocessed and has been interfiled.
Additions (Acc. 2005-0067) (1875 items, 3.0 lin. ft.; dated 1990s-2003) and (Acc. 2004-0133) (2 items, 0.1 lin. ft.; dated 2004) comprise manuscripts, drafts, notes, typescripts, and correspondence for Double Vision, The Year in Fiction, and Every Bitter Thing. Also includes typescripts, notes, holograph manuscripts, and typescripts with holograph corrections for essays, stories, and other writings; and a broadside of Garrett's poem, Luck's Shinning Child, printed for the 2004 Virginia Festival of the Book.
The addition (Acc. 2006-0090) (750 items, 1.2 lin. ft.; dated 2005-2006) contains proofs for Bad Man Blues and The King of Babylon Shall not Come Against You.; manuscripts for Godfather and several short stories; print materials including books and journals authored or edited by Garrett; 2 DVDs; and 12 computer diskettes. The content of these diskettes has been migrated to archival storage server. Closed pending processing.
The addition (Acc. 2007-0075)(5,400 items; 7.2 lin. ft.; dated 1971-2006) primarily contains drafts of Garrett's writings as typescripts and electronic files on diskettes. Also included are books and journals that feature his works and works of other authors; audiocassettes and CDs of interviews and readings by Garrett; and correspondence. Closed pending processing.
The addition (Acc. 2008-0181) (760 items; 1.2 lin. ft.; dated 1999-2008) contains notes, research, and drafts of Garrett’s short story The Source, eventually renamed Thanksgiving. There are also some folders of correspondence, transcripts of interviews, and some audiovisual material including four audiocassette tapes and one DVD.
The addition (Acc. 2008-0271) (375 items; 0.6 lin. ft.; dated 1985-2008) contains correspondence; drafts and notes for poems and other projects, including an Armies of Occupation project; and copies of newspaper clippings and interviews with Garrett.
Addition (Acc. 2013-0168) (50 items, 0.1 lin. ft.; dated 1964-1972) comprises a file of letters to Garrett from those whose last names begin with the letter "P."
Subject Headings
Garrett, George P., 1929-; Wilkinson, Sylvia, 1940-; Chappell, Fred, 1936-; Chappell, Fred, 1936-; Price, Reynolds, 1933-; Bell, Madison Smartt; American literature -- Southern States; Periodical editors -- United States -- Correspondence; Literature -- Study and teaching; Motion picture plays -- United States; Authors and publishers; Authors, American -- 20th century -- Correspondence; Audiocassettes; Videocassettes
Related Material
Stuart Wright Bibliographic Collection of George Garrett, 1951-1993 and undated
Rubenstein Library, Duke University
Contents of Collection
- Writings Series, 1957-1996 and undated
  The Writings Series is divided into four subseries: Writings by Garrett, Writings Edited by Garrett, Writings by Others, and Proofs.
  - Writings by Garrett Subseries, 1957-1996 and undated
    Manuscripts, typescripts, and drafts of Garrett's published works, some bearing notations by Garrett. Categories include: Monographs (arranged chronologically in order of publication date of work), Dramatic Works and Short Stories (arranged alphabetically by title), Reviews (arranged alphabetically by the name of the author of the work being reviewed), Literary Essays and Biographies (arranged alphabetically by title), and Miscellaneous Writings and fragments (unarranged).
    - Monographs
      - 1957, King of the Mountain, (11 folders) (Box WG 1)
      - 1958, Sleeping Gypsy, (6 folders) (Box WG 1)
      - 1959, The Finished Man, (7 folders) (Box WG 1)
      - 1961, Abraham's Knife, (8 folders) (Box WG 1)
      - 1961, In the Briar Patch, (13 folders) (Box WG 1)
      - 1961, Which Ones are the Enemy?, (3 folders) (Box WG 1)
      - 1964, Cold Ground Was My Bed Last Night, (25 folders) (Box WG 2)
      - 1965, Do, Lord, Remember Me, (7 folders) (Box WG 2)
      - 1965, Do, Lord, Remember Me, (32 folders) (Box WG 3)
      - 1965, Do, Lord, Remember Me, (7 folders) (Box WG 4)
      - 1967, For a Bitter Season, (40 folders) (Box WG 4)
      - 1971, Death of the Fox, (7 folders) (Box WG 4)
      - 1971, Death of the Fox, (40 folders) (Box WG 5)
      - 1971, Death of the Fox, (42 folders) (Box WG 6)
      - 1971, Death of the Fox, (39 folders) (Box WG 7)
      - 1971, Death of the Fox, (18 folders) (Box WG 8)
      - 1971, Death of the Fox 43 folders) (Box WG 9)
      - 1973, The Magic Striptease, (29 folders) (Box WG 10)
      - 1978, Welcome to the Medicine Show, (8 folders) (Box WG 10)
      - 1981, Luck's Shining Child, (9 folders) (Box WG 10)
      - 1983, The Succession: Elizabeth and James, (50 folders) (Box WG 11)
      - 1983, The Succession: Elizabeth and James, (23 folders) (Box WG 12)
      - 1983, The Succession: Elizabeth and James, (43 folders) (Box WG 13)
      - 1983, The Succession: Elizabeth and James, (51 folders) (Box WG 14)
      - 1983, The Succession: Elizabeth and James, (38 folders) (Box WG 15)
      - 1983, The Succession: Elizabeth and James, (17 folders) (Box WG 16)
      - 1983, The Succession: Elizabeth and James, (36 folders) (Box WG 17)
      - 1983, The Succession: Elizabeth and James, (65 folders) (Box WG 18)
      - 1983, The Succession: Elizabeth and James, (27 folders) (Box WG 19)
      - 1983, The Succession: Elizabeth and James, (66 folders) (Box WG 20)
      - 1983, The Succession: Elizabeth and James, (49 folders) (Box WG 21)
      - 1983, The Succession: Elizabeth and James, (21 folders) (Box WG 22)
      - 1984, James Jones, (14 folders) (Box WG 22)
      - 1984, James Jones, (16 folders) (Box WG 23)
      - 1985, An Evening Performance, (24 folders) (Box WG 24)
      - 1985, Life with Kim Novak is Hell, (24 folders) (Box WG 24)
      - 1985, Life with Kim Novak is Hell, (21 folders) (Box WG 25)
      - 1986, Poison Pen, (34 folders) (Box WG 25)
      - 1986, Poison Pen, (2 folders) (Box WG 26)
      - 1988, Understanding Mary Lee Settle, (17 folders) (Box WG 26)
      - 1988, Understanding Mary Lee Settle, (1 folder) (Box WG 27)
      - 1990, Entered from the Sun, (20 folders) (Box WG 27)
      - 1990, Entered from the Sun, (23 folders) (Box WG 28)
      - 1990, Entered from the Sun, (33 folders) (Box WG 29)
      - 1990, Entered from the Sun, (30 folders) (Box WG 30)
      - 1990, Entered from the Sun, (3 folders) (Box WG 31)
      - 1992, My Silk Purse and Yours, (7 folders) (Box WG 31)
      - 1992, Sorrows of Fat City, (1 folder) (Box WG 31)
      - 1992, Whistling in the Dark, (9 folders) (Box WG 31)
      - 1992, Whistling in the Dark, (18 folders) (Box WG 32)
      - 1994, The Old Army Game, (15 folders) (Box WG 32)
      - 1996, King of Babylon, (3 folders) (Box WG 32)
    - Dramatic Works
      - The Acting Lesson, (1 folder) (Box WG 33)
      - Ajax, (1 folder) (Box WG 33)
      - Alexander the Great, (2 folders) (Box WG 33)
      - And So Love Came to Alfred Zeer, (2 folders) (Box WG 33)
      - The Architect, (1 folder) (Box WG 33)
      - Assassins, (1 folder) (Box WG 33)
      - The Best Man, (1 folder) (Box WG 33)
      - The Binge, (11 folders) (Box WG 33)
      - Charade, (1 folder) (Box WG 33)
      - Children of the Dark Gods, (1 folder) (Box WG 33)
      - Cold Ground Was My Bed Last Night, (3 folders) (Box WG 33)
      - Daughter of the Dark Gods, (1 folder) (Box WG 33)
      - Day of Reckoning, (2 folders) (Box WG 33)
      - Don't Take No for an Answer, (3 folders) (Box WG 33)
      - Do You Remember the Time in Florida?, (2 folders) (Box WG 33)
      - Elizabeth and Delancey, (1 folder) (Box WG 34)
      - Enchanted Ground, (8 folders) (Box WG 34)
      - The Entrepreneur, (1 folder) (Box WG 34)
      - The Farmer in the Dell, (1 folder) (Box WG 34)
      - Flesh, (1 folder) (Box WG 34)
      - Frankenstein Meets the Space Monster, (7 folders) (Box WG 34)
      - Futura, (2 folders) (Box WG 34)
      - Garden Spot, U.S.A., (8 folders) (Box WG 34)
      - Gentleman from Georgia, (1 folder) (Box WG 34)
      - Good Friday, (1 folder) (Box WG 35)
      - The Hussar, (1 folder) (Box WG 35)
      - King of the Mountain, (2 folders) (Box WG 35)
      - Knight of the Kitchen, (2 folders) (Box WG 35)
      - Little Tune for a Steel String Guitar, (1 folder) (Box WG 35)
      - Magic City, (11 folders) (Box WG 35)
      - Magic Striptease, (2 folders) (Box WG 35)
      - Man without a Figleaf, (1 folder) (Box WG 35)
      - The Moth, (1 folder) (Box WG 35)
      - My Brother, Death, (1 folder) (Box WG 35)
      - My Picture Left in Scotland, (1 folder) (Box WG 35)
      - Noise of Strangers, (1 folder) (Box WG 35)
      - Old Knight, (1 folder) (Box WG 35)
      - 3 Myths from Ovid, (1 folder) (Box WG 35)
      - The Playground, (1 folder) (Box WG 35)
      - Prism, (1 folder) (Box WG 35)
      - Sir Slob and the Princess, (4 folders) (Box WG 35)
      - Snead and Frumley, (1 folder) (Box WG 35)
      - Song of a Drowning Sailor, (1 folder) (Box WG 35)
      - Time of Assassins, (1 folder) (Box WG 35)
      - Unfortunate Lover, (1 folder) (Box WG 35)
      - Which Ones are My Enemies?, (1 folder) (Box WG 35)
      - The Word, the Flesh, and a Smiling Girl, (1 folder) (Box WG 35)
      - Wounded Soldier, (1 folder) (Box WG 35)
      - Young Lovers, (2 folders) (Box WG 35)
    - Short Stories
      - The Active Garden, (1 folder) (Box WG 36)
      - Al, (1 folder) (Box WG 36)
      - Alpha, (1 folder) (Box WG 36)
      - And So Love Came to Alfred Zeer, (1 folder) (Box WG 36)
      - Another Abdication, (1 folder) (Box WG 36)
      - Arlette of Falaise, (1 folder) (Box WG 36)
      - As travellers from far places..., (1 folder) (Box WG 36)
      - Atom Christ, (1 folder) (Box WG 36)
      - Atos, (1 folder) (Box WG 36)
      - A Bad Boy, (1 folder) (Box WG 36)
      - Beach Party, (1 folder) (Box WG 36)
      - Bedtime Story, (1 folder) (Box WG 36)
      - Bennington, (1 folder) (Box WG 36)
      - Black Man, (1 folder) (Box WG 36)
      - Big Tall Ghost of F. Scott Fitzgerald, (1 folder) (Box WG 36)
      - Blow Out the Candle, (2 folders) (Box WG 36)
      - Blues, (1 folder) (Box WG 36)
      - The Bride, (1 folder) (Box WG 36)
      - Casual Magnolia, (1 folder) (Box WG 36)
      - The Cave, (1 folder) (Box WG 36)
      - Clyde Crabtree, (1 folder) (Box WG 36)
      - The Coin, (1 folder) (Box WG 36)
      - Color of a Sigh..., (1 folder) (Box WG 36)
      - Conshoken, (1 folder) (Box WG 36)
      - Conversation at Princeton Station, (1 folder) (Box WG 36)
      - Days of Our Lives..., (2 folders) (Box WG 36)
      - Dear John, (2 folders) (Box WG 36)
      - Dear Ralph Ellison, (1 folder) (Box WG 36)
      - Death of Garden Spot, (1 folder) (Box WG 36)
      - Decline and Fall of Dave O'Hara, (2 folders) (Box WG 36)
      - A Dirty Story, (1 folder) (Box WG 36)
      - Divine Wind, (1 folder) (Box WG 36)
      - Dixie Dreamland, (2 folders) (Box WG 36)
      - Don't Look Now Mother..., (1 folder) (Box WG 36)
      - Drink Muddy Water, (1 folder) (Box WG 36)
      - Entered from the Sun, (1 folder) (Box WG 36)
      - Epigram, (1 folder) (Box WG 36)
      - Epigraph #2, (1 folder) (Box WG 36)
      - Epilogue, (1 folder) (Box WG 36)
      - Escapes, (3 folders) (Box WG 36)
      - The Experiment, (1 folder) (Box WG 36)
      - Fable of the Times, (1 folder) (Box WG 36)
      - Fabliaux (, (1 folder) (Box WG 36)
      - Faiths are a forest..., (1 folder) (Box WG 36)
      - Farewell All Joys, (1 folder) (Box WG 36)
      - Feeling Good, Feeling Fine, (1 folder) (Box WG 36)
      - Figure of Speech, (1 folder) (Box WG 36)
      - Fin de Siecle, (1 folder) (Box WG 36)
      - Final Tape of Dr. Wisdom, (1 folder) (Box WG 36)
      - Flamenco Dancer, (1 folder) (Box WG 36)
      - Flash Cards, (2 folders) (Box WG 36)
      - Floogie, (2 folders) (Box WG 36)
      - for 'Milkshake', (1 folder) (Box WG 36)
      - from 'Lives of Poets ', (1 folder) (Box WG 36)
      - Genius Baby, (1 folder) (Box WG 36)
      - Gentleman from Georgia, (1 folder) (Box WG 36)
      - Gesture of Circe, (1 folder) (Box WG 36)
      - Ghosts, (1 folder) (Box WG 36)
      - Girl with the Marble Thigh, (5 folders) (Box WG 36)
      - Glass Jaw, (1 folder) (Box WG 36)
      - Good-bye to the Ice Cream Kingdom, (1 folder) (Box WG 36)
      - Good Evening..., (1 folder) (Box WG 36)
      - Good Fridays, (1 folder) (Box WG 36)
      - Guitar Themes, (1 folder) (Box WG 36)
      - Harrangue by a Clown..., (1 folder) (Box WG 36)
      - Here Comes the Bride, (3 folders) (Box WG 36)
      - The Hollins Conference, (1 folder) (Box WG 36)
      - Hounds of Actaeon, (1 folder) (Box WG 36)
      - Houston, (1 folder) (Box WG 36)
      - How Can You Tell...?, (1 folder) (Box WG 36)
      - Hunter's View, (1 folder) (Box WG 36)
      - I read the death of Whitman's dream, (1 folder) (Box WG 36)
      - I Say It's Spinach, (2 folders) (Box WG 36)
      - I stand on the threshold..., (1 folder) (Box WG 36)
      - I Will Sing for You Sweetly, (1 folder) (Box WG 36)
      - If the Phone Rings, Don't Answer, (1 folder) (Box WG 36)
      - In a Bad Time, (1 folder) (Box WG 36)
      - In the Time of Tall Kings, (1 folder) (Box WG 36)
      - Inch by Inch, (1 folder) (Box WG 36)
      - Inertia, (1 folder) (Box WG 36)
      - Intoxicants..., (1 folder) (Box WG 36)
      - Invention of Canasta, (1 folder) (Box WG 36)
      - It is the Winter Wind (, (1 folder) (Box WG 36)
      - It's like Groundhog Day..., (1 folder) (Box WG 36)
      - J.T. writes another poem..., (1 folder) (Box WG 36)
      - Justice, (1 folder) (Box WG 36)
      - The Lady Diana Takes Tea, (1 folder) (Box WG 36)
      - Land of the Magic Forest, (1 folder) (Box WG 36)
      - The Last Magician, (1 folder) (Box WG 36)
      - The Legacy and Berrying, (1 folder) (Box WG 36)
      - Leon Waddell, (1 folder) (Box WG 36)
      - Lesson for Today, (1 folder) (Box WG 36)
      - Letter to a Scholar, (1 folder) (Box WG 36)
      - Linz, Austria, (1 folder) (Box WG 36)
      - Little Song, (1 folder) (Box WG 36)